<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<info:toolkitInfoModel xmlns:common="http://www.ibm.com/xmlns/prod/streams/spl/common" xmlns:info="http://www.ibm.com/xmlns/prod/streams/spl/toolkitInfo">
  <info:identity>
    <info:name>com.ibm.streamsx.objectstorage</info:name>
    <info:description>
The Object Storage toolkit is an open source IBM Streams toolkit that helps you integrate IBM Streams with IBM Cloud Object Storage.

The operators provide the ability for IBM Streams applications to write objects to object storage and read objects from object storage.

The operators support IBM Cloud Object Storage and S3 compatible object storages.

The Object Storage toolkit operators must be configured to connect to S3 compatible object storages. This connection information needs to be specified with operator parameters or application configuration.

The toolkit contains two namespaces:

* com.ibm.streamsx.objectstorage
* com.ibm.streamsx.objectstorage.s3

Operators in the `com.ibm.streamsx.objectstorage` use generic parameters approach rather the operators in the `com.ibm.streamsx.objectstorage.s3` namespace use S3-compliant authentication and connection parameters.
For example, `ObjectStorageSink` uses `objectStorageURI` parameter which consists of protocol and bucket name (s3a://&lt;BUCKET_NAME&gt;/), rather `S3ObjectStorageSink` operator uses S3-compliant parameter names such as protocol and bucket as a separate parameters making it more intuitive for the users familiar with S3 COS terms.
Note, that other operator parameter groups (except of authentication and connection) are exactly the same for both operators.

+ What's new

This is an overview of changes for major and minor version upgrades. For details, see the releases in public [https://github.com/IBMStreams/streamsx.objectstorage/releases|GitHub].

++ What is new in version 1.9.0

* ObjectStorageScan, ObjectStorageSource and ObjectStorageSink operator: New parameter `credentials` has been introduced. It supports to set the raw JSON of the IBM COS service.
* Parameters `IAMApiKey`, `IAMServiceInstanceId` and `IAMTokenEndpoint` are deprecated. It is recommended to use the `credentials` parameter to set the IBM COS service credentials.

++ What is new in version 1.8.0

* ObjectStorageSink operator: Provides the new variable part '%CHANNEL' for building the object name. Use this when your operator is part of a [https://www.ibm.com/support/knowledgecenter/en/SSCRJU_4.3.0/com.ibm.streams.dev.doc/doc/udpoverview.html|parallel region] and the channel number should be part of the objectname to avoid name clashes.
* ObjectStorageSource operator: Changed the trace level from 'info' to 'trace' for per-tuple traces. 
* Documentation improvements.

+ Using the toolkit with IBM Cloud Object Storage

# Before you begin

Create an instance of [https://console.bluemix.net/docs/services/cloud-object-storage/getting-started.html|IBM COS].

# Create IBM COS service credentials

Use the following steps to create a service credential:

1. Log in to the IBM Cloud console and navigate to your instance of Object Storage.
2. In the side navigation, click Service Credentials.
3. Click New credential and provide the necessary information.
4. Click Add to generate service credential.
5. Click View credentials and copy JSON into clipboard.
		
# Save Credentials in Application Configuration Property

Store IBM Cloud Object Storage Credentials JSON in an application configuration property called `cos.creds`.
When the operator starts, it will look for that property and extract the information needed to connect.

The following steps outline how this can be done:

1. Create an application configuration called `cos`.
2. Create a property in the `cos` application configuration *named* `cos.creds`. The *value* of the property should be the raw IBM Cloud Object Storage Credentials JSON
3. The operator will automatically look for an application configuration named `cos` and will extract the information needed to connect.


+ Developing and running applications that use the ObjectStorage Toolkit

To create applications that use the ObjectStorage Toolkit, you must configure either Streams Studio
or the SPL compiler to be aware of the location of the toolkit. 

# Before you begin

* Install IBM Streams. Configure the product environment variables by entering the following command: 
      &lt;source product-installation-root-directory>/&lt;your version>/bin/streamsprofile.sh


# About this task

After the location of the toolkit is communicated to the compiler, the SPL artifacts that are specified in the toolkit
can be used by an application. The application can include a use directive to bring the necessary namespaces into scope.
Alternatively, you can fully qualify the operators that are provided by toolkit with their namespaces as prefixes.

# Procedure

1. Review the list of restrictions for the IBM Streams specialized toolkits in the product documentation.
2. Configure the SPL compiler to find the toolkit root directory. Use one of the following methods:
  * Set the **STREAMS_SPLPATH** environment variable to the root directory of a toolkit or multiple toolkits (with : as a separator).
    For example:
        export STREAMS_SPLPATH=$STREAMS_INSTALL/toolkits/com.ibm.streamsx.objectstorage
  * Specify the **-t** or **--spl-path** command parameter when you run the **sc** command. For example:
        sc -t $STREAMS_INSTALL/toolkits/com.ibm.streamsx.objectstorage -M MyMain
    where MyMain is the name of the SPL main composite.
    **Note**: These command parameters override the **STREAMS_SPLPATH** environment variable.
  * Add the toolkit location in Streams Studio.
3. Develop your application. To avoid the need to fully qualify the operators, add a use directive in your application. 
  * For example, you can add the following clause in your SPL source file:
        use com.ibm.streamsx.objectstorage::*;
    You can also specify a use clause for individual operators by replacing the asterisk (\*) with the operator name. For example: 
        use com.ibm.streamsx.objectstorage::ObjectStorageSink; 
4. Build your application. You can use the **sc** command or Streams Studio.  
5. Start the IBM Streams instance. 
6. Run the application. You can submit the application as a job by using the **streamtool submitjob** command or by using Streams Studio. 


+ Protocol (client) selection

{doc/images/SinkLayers.png}

The diagram represents represents two different clients which are utilized by the toolkit:
* hadoop-aws (s3a protocol)
* stocator (cos protocol)

You may easily select one of the two S3 clients by specifying appropriate protocol in the `objectStorageURI` parameter.
The URI should be in `cos://bucket/` or `s3a://bucket/` format. Replace bucket with the name of the bucket you created.
Concretely, when **s3a** protocol is specified the toolkit uses *hadoop-aws* client. When **cos** protocol is specified the toolkit uses *stocator* client.

Note: The S3ObjectStorageSink, S3ObjectStorageSource and S3ObjectStorageScan operators have a `protocol` parameter for the client selection and a `bucket` parameter to specify the name of the bucket.

For ObjectStorageScan and ObjectStorageSource operator there is no big difference regarding the S3 client and you can select any of both clients.
The ObjectStorageSink works different depending on the client selection.

Recommendation for client selection when writing objects in raw or parquet format:

* Your application creates large objects one after another, then select s3a protocol, because large objects are uploaded in multiple parts in parallel.
* Your application creates many objects within a narrow time frame, then select cos protocol, because multiple threads are uploading the entire object per thread in parallel.

When writing objects in *partitioned parquet* format both clients work similar and you may select one of the clients because of the different buffering mechanism:

* hadoop-aws (s3a protocol): supports buffering in memory or disk (parameter `s3aFastUploadBuffer`) - **default**: **memory buffer** prior upload
* stocator (cos protocol): buffers on local disk prior upload

</info:description>
    <info:version>1.9.1.__dev__</info:version>
    <info:requiredProductVersion>4.2.0.0</info:requiredProductVersion>
  </info:identity>
  <info:dependencies/>
</info:toolkitInfoModel>
